so Jane if you wanted to close off your
your camera and then
as we get going because when we start
it'll just be me and then we'll open it
up to the two presentations and then the
Round Table
um for question period if questions come
up in the chat is someone monitoring
them or do we read them and okay good
stuff thank you
so yeah if they come up while you're
presenting I'll ask them at the end
um just it makes
depending on how detailed it is I may
ask it at the end of your presentation
or save it until the end end but we'll
play it by ear
terrific thank you
and what I'll do too is when you start
I'll I'll hide my my face as well just
so that there's there's just you talking
to your slides just makes it easier sure
okay
for those of you joining we're just
going to give it a few minutes we'll
probably start at about 11 31.
thank you
no
foreign
oh yeah
but we have a huge amount on our plate
to present to you so I don't want to
delay it much longer so welcome to our
sixth installment of the financial
literacy webinar series
that is being co-hosted between 369
Global and uh the Canadian ETF
Association my name is Pat Dunwoody and
I'm the executive director of the
Canadian ETF Association and I'm
thrilled to have a large group to be
able to present to you so that we'll be
able to answer any and all of your
questions that come forward
Insurance can be a complicated item and
thing to think about protecting yourself
and your loved ones shouldn't be
shouldn't have to be so we wanted to
take the mystery out of insurance so you
can learn how it works how it benefits
you and your family and make sure you
get the most out of it
I'll facilitate today's session and we
have two present presentations and then
a panel of insurance experts to answer
first uh questions that I have and then
we'll open it up to you to ask any
questions that you may have
so we're going to start today with
Anne-Marie Thomas the director of
consumer and Industry relations at the
insurance Bureau of Canada
followed by a presentation by Brent
Missin the assistant vice president of
Market conduct at the Canadian health
and Life Insurance Association and then
we'll move into a panel discussion with
insurance agents from Sun Life that will
be able to answer specific questions
so with that and I don't want to take
any more time so Anne-Marie over to you
thank you very much and welcome everyone
I'm going to be doing two presentations
for you today
um super high level the first one is on
auto insurance and the second one is on
home tenant insurance so I'm going to
share my screen here now
and I hope that everyone can see that
okay
so this is everything you want to know
about auto insurance in Emory and we're
not seeing we're not seeing your screen
yet
oh okay I thought it was there okay let
me try it again
share screen
this one
how is that
are you seeing it yes that's fine thank
you okay terrific okay so the this is um
you know a super high level about
everything you need to know about
Ontario Auto Insurance
so just to step back a little bit uh can
Canada's private Property and Casualty
Insurance industry employs 130
000 people across Canada now that was in
2020. insurance companies paid out a
total of 42 billion dollars in claims to
victims of collisions disasters and
other losses in Canada again that's 2020
data in 2020 Canadian insurers uh wrote
71 billion dollars in direct written
premiums for insurance on consumers
homes cars and businesses and the cons
and the insurance Property and Casualty
industry
contributed uh over 10 billion dollars
in taxis levies and fees to the federal
and provincial governments in 2019.
so how does auto insurance work
so drivers make a payment to their
insurance companies and those are called
premiums and all of those premiums are
pulled together to make up a collection
of funds the from those funds uh
insurance companies pay out uh to repair
your car or to pay if you're injured
after an auto action
so what does an auto insurance covers
auto insurance cover is sort of
unexpected events and it protects you
from Financial stress if you have to pay
for car repairs or if you're injured
health care costs in 2020 insurance
companies paid out on average
161 500 to a person injured in a
collision that's not even including what
they paid to fix a person's car so for
for the on average if a person was
injured in an auto accident
and insurance companies paid out 161 500
in medical
so what do you need to know about Auto
Insurance
an auto insurance policy is in essence a
legal contract between you as the owner
of the vehicle and your insurance
company they are typically for a fixed
period time on average at the uh an auto
insurance policy is issued for a year
and it's a policy of indemnities or
another word for an Indemnity is like a
promise so the insurance company
promises that if you get into an auto
accident they will pay to repair your
vehicle or if you're injured to pay your
medical costs you promise that you will
pay your insurance premiums so it's um
it is a policy of promise and
interestingly enough it's one of the few
things in our lives we buy that we hope
that we never have to use
so there is a myth that insurance is
like a bank account that you can
withdraw from to pay for your car
insurance damage and that's not true
auto insurance is is should be looked at
as a safety net to cover costs if you
are ever in a collision an insurance an
auto insurance policy is not a
maintenance policy for your car there
have to be very specific things that
happen uh in order for an insurance
policy to kick in so that would have to
be
uh you know you're actually involved in
a collision not for something like wear
and tear on your car new tires oil
changes that sort of thing that's not
what an auto insurance policy is for
so one of the questions that we get a
lot is well why do I need auto insurance
well the first reason is it's a law
anyone who owns and drives a vehicle in
the province of Ontario must have valid
auto insurance the penalty is quite
Hefty if you're convicted of driving
without insurance it's thousands of
dollars it and it's uh and in fines and
it's increased insurance premiums for
years after if you're convicted
another reason that you need uh auto
insurance is that it protects your
financial situation so if we look back
to what the average uh injury payout was
it was 161 000 imagine if you had to pay
that yourself that could be financially
crippling to some families
and having valid insurance protects your
driving privileges if you don't have
insurance you can have your license
suspended you can you know as I
mentioned you can face Hefty fines so
it's not worth it to drive without
insurance
so how is your insurance premium
calculated
there are a number of things that are
taken into consideration in determining
the premium or the rate that you pay so
one of the factors is you so your
driving history so how many tickets
accidents do you have on your record
where do you live because if you live in
in a major metropolitan area like
Toronto it's likely going to cost you
more than if you live in a remote area
with very few cars and very few risk of
accidents your age will affect your
premium and the type of car you drive as
well as how you drive so where how many
kilometers a day week year do you drive
do you drive to work you'll pay more for
insurance than if you're a work from
home
um the other rating factors is the
insurance company that you're with their
overall claims experience so what I mean
by that is how much have it has your
insurance company paid to uh in in total
claims in a year a company that has paid
out more in claims than another company
is likely going to have uh higher
insurance rates than a company whose
insurance payouts are less so it's
important to know
um
uh you know it's important to shop
around uh to uh find the best rate for
your profile
so what are you covered for when you buy
an auto insurance policy well the
mandatory coverage that you have to have
is a minimum of two hundred thousand
third party liability and accident
benefits and uninsured auto insurance
coverage they're all purchased as a
package in addition to the mandatory you
can purchase optional coverage so you
have the option to buy comprehensive or
Collision coverage and that is for
damage to your vehicle so comprehensive
coverage will cover things
um such as vandalism theft falling
object so if a tree falls on your car
you're covered Collision will cover
damage
to your vehicle if you are in an at
fault accident if you are in a not at
fault accident your own policy will pay
will pay you don't have to have
purchased Collision Collision is only
beneficial if you're the if you were at
fault
so it's important to keep your insurance
valid
so avoid getting tickets any speeding
tickets Red Light tickets careless
driving or impaired driving distracted
driving all could play a part in the
premium that you pay uh so for example
someone convicted of careless driving or
or uh you know texting while driving
they could see their insurance premium
double at minimum for years
so a ticket can stay on your driving
record for up to three years and the
premium you pay for insurance may be
increased for the length of time that
those convictions are on your record
stint insurance is mandatory to drive in
the province of Ontario there is what is
called the facility Association and
that's where if you have too many
tickets and or too many accidents and no
regular Market insurance company wants
to insure you then you would go into the
facility Association which has you know
sort of a last resort and it is
incredibly expensive to get insurance
so tips for buying insurance
most people say auto insurance is too
high and and I can't disagree with you
so there are a couple of ways that you
can look to reduce the cost of your auto
insurance so choose a higher deductible
and the deductible is typically on the
collision and comprehensive portions of
your policy and what a deductible is is
the portion of a claim that you will pay
typically a deductible for collision and
comprehensive is five hundred dollars so
if your claim is for four thousand
dollars you pay the first 500 the
insurance company will pay the remaining
three thousand five hundred
so the tip typically the higher the
deductible that you pay the lower your
premium will be
another tip to helping to control your
auto insurance premium is shop around
not all insurance companies have the
same premium for the same driver profile
we remember I spoke briefly about
insurance companies claims experience so
you want to make sure that you're with
the company that offers the lowest rate
for your profile so shop around get
multiple quotes and pay the lowest rate
that you can
there are some other ways that you can
save a lot of companies offer you a
discount if you put your home
or tenant policy with your auto policy
um a lot of people don't know
what discounts may be available to them
so ask your insurance company about
discounts some insurance companies have
group discounts based on employer or
alumni associations they may offer you a
discount if you install a telematics
device into your car and what that is is
a device that monitors your driving so
okay
if you have great driving habits your
insurance company may offer you a
discount for simply installing a
telematics device in your car most
insurance companies will offer a minimum
of five percent discount
so what happens if you need to file a
claim
so you find your insurance card call
your insurance companies emergency
claims line for help
remember if you're at fault in an
accident
that at fault accident may cause your
insurance premium to rise
and if you have any questions about your
insurance Insurance Bureau of Canada has
a consumer information center that you
can reach out at
1-844-227-5422 you can call there and
ask any insurance question that you have
but if you have a complaint the best
thing to do is to start with your
insurance companies ombuds person
insurance companies all have an ombuds
person that you can find on the
insurance company website and if your
claim complaint is not in your uh result
you can reach out to the superintendent
of insurance for Auto
thank you for that portion I know it was
very quick so please don't hesitate if
you have any other questions and I'm
reading just one thing just a very quick
question from somebody in the audience
is that if somebody gets a speeding
ticket but it but they didn't have
points would this still impact their
insurance yes it would uh it's so it's
occurrences that affect your premium so
for example if you have two speeding
tickets but you don't get any points the
insurance company still looks at it as
you have uh two instances
um when you have higher points generally
the severity of the infraction is
greater and so for example careless
driving that's always going to increase
your premium because it's a more serious
conviction
okay and another quick one and I may ask
you to do your second part after Brett's
just because we're getting questions if
a family member has a g G2 do I need to
include them in my insurance yes uh a G2
is a a fully is a is that full is a
license unlike a G1 which is a permit so
the auto insurance application asks you
to list licensed drivers in the
household so since the G2 is a license
you should be letting your insurance
company know that you have that driver
living in the household who may drive
your vehicle
so even if they don't drive it's it's
that they have a license correct because
the potential is there for them to drive
okay and last question and if you don't
mind we'll go to Brent because I'm
conscious of time one last question how
about parking tickets
parking tickets do not parking tickets
red light cameras
um there are some Municipal calming area
cameras that issue tickets those do not
affect your driving record because those
are attached to your license plate not
your driving license you still have to
pay those fines but they won't affect
your auto insurance premium perfect
thank you very much so if you don't mind
we'll flip to Brent's now okay
I'm going to stop sharing there we go
thanks very much Anne-Marie that was
really helpful okay now friends over to
you
okay thank you so I will see if I can
share my screen here
does that look okay there
coming on it will be there shortly I'm
thinking it's it's thinking about it it
says there we go
very I've got part of your screen
oh yeah it's only doing part
let me try that one more time
just let me know if that comes up
thinking
there we go perfect okay so we'll run
through so thank you very much for
having me I'm uh Brent Nissen assistant
Vice President of America conduct uh
policy and regulation at uh Canadian
life and health insurance Association so
what I'm going to talk today a little
bit about
um is one the industry uh what the
industry does and then we'll talk a
little bit more specifically about
um some of the insurance products and
we'll focus mostly uh on life insurance
that tends to be one of the greatest
interests but but it's certainly not the
the only one
uh so just try and Advance the slide
here so the first part just a little bit
about clhra so we the Indus industry
associate Association are are not for
profit uh we're a member-based
Association we represent 99
uh of the life and health insurance
companies
um and in terms of the companies
themselves there are 63 companies
um and and there's generally four types
um you'll see there there's there's 47
life insurance companies
um and then we move down to
not-for-profit Health Care Providers we
also have fraternal benefit societies
and then there's Property and Casualty
insurers that offer health benefits as
well
and I mentioned a lot of the focus of
the talk today will be on life insurance
that's but that's one of three buckets
uh when you look at the the companies
there's there's life insurance products
denoted by gray uh there's health
insurance products denoted by green and
there's Retirement Solutions which are
denoted by Blue
um and if you look at the the pie shaped
charts on the screen you can see uh
there's a wide range some go from fully
gray so focus on life insurance some
have Retirement Solutions focused and
then others are a mix in between so
there so there is some variability in
there
in terms of the coverage uh and benefit
profile for the industry for 2021.
um overall in 2021 life and health
insurers provided Financial Protection
uh for 29 million Canadians
um and paid out 113 billion dollars in
benefits so so fairly substantial in in
providing protection to to Canadians and
then if we look a little further down
into categories we see life insurance
covers 22 million
and life insurance benefits payouts in
in 2021 were 14.3 billion dollars
if we then take a look at health
insurance that covers 27 million
Canadians so again very significant
there
um and that that the benefits payout is
40.8 billion dollars in health insurance
uh and and in the next slide we'll we'll
dig down a little deeper on on the
health insurance and what that includes
but one of the the key aspects there is
prescription drug coverage
uh and then the last last category uh in
the blue is retirement which covers
eight million Canadians
um and that covers in terms of benefit
pay that's 58.1 billion you also see on
the slide there that includes annuity
payments on employer sponsored or
individual products uh and that they
have nearly doubled in the last decade
in terms of what an annuity payment is
that's a a stream of payments
um uh that's that's guaranteed uh over a
certain period of time
the other important thing that that will
speak to
um is group versus life insurance and
we'll go into this in a little more
detail in a little bit but just in terms
of how that breaks down you see 66
percent is sold as group uh group you
can think of in a couple of ways
probably the classic example is Group
Insurance is is part of your employment
benefits whereas for individual
insurance that's something you uh would
buy for example to protect you and your
family in the event of an unforeseen uh
event
make sure we dig down a little bit more
um just in terms of the the health
benefits coverage
um and and you can see here clearly
um what what your large portion is uh in
terms of the the blue category
um and I mentioned that prescription
drugs uh represent a fairly substantial
portion of that at 13.4 billion uh but
the other coverage provided there is
also uh really important it goes include
Dental Hospital Vision massage
Chiropractic
physiotherapy certainly mental health
has become a very important component
particularly through the pandemic and as
we make our way out of it
um in the green uh we know disability
there both short term and long term and
then accident and other and and other
can include things like critical illness
long-term care insurance and so on so so
those those
benefits are very important to Canadians
and provide a really important
protection or Safety Net in addition to
coverage they may have for example
through through government programs
Now we move into understanding a little
bit about insurance and Emory's
presentation touched on some things that
are similar between life and health
insurance
and Property and Casualty Insurance and
then we also have some differences so
I'll try to highlight those as we go
through first one of the similarities
insurance is a contract that provides
financial protection against anticipated
loss and unanticipated losses underlying
there
um let's take a look at life insurance
for example certainly what what what
you're trying to protect against for
life insurance
is an earlier premature death and you
want to protect against the financial
impacts that could be felt by your loved
ones for example your family
there are different types of insurance
at the at the highest level you can
differentiate between public sector and
private sector our industry's private
sector
and then if we look at what the public
to provide you can get insurance through
the Canadian pension plan or come back
to qpp
Employment Insurance there's workers
compensation as well as health insurance
provided by the provinces and then our
industry and our members provide a range
of uh products that provide Financial
Protection who spoke about life pensions
and annuities disability critical
illness long-term care as well as health
care and dental care so a wide range
there
in terms of principles of insurance and
and this is important to understand when
we consider life insurance for example
spreading of risk across large groups uh
is important and offers a lot of
benefits
um and and the benefit clearly the
benefit there is a law of large numbers
that allows you to ensure
um a group that if you were to
underwrite someone only on their their
own and only consider their risk it
would be much more expensive and
challenging to do it that way so so the
law of large numbers is is to to our
advantage
um premiums charge should reflect the
applicant's risk that's an important
point also you want like Risk to receive
similar premiums in other words if
someone is a higher risk they should be
prior to premium that is similar to
someone else that is of a similar high
risk
um and and sort of flowing from that is
we pool risks that are similar together
and not then feeds back to the spreading
of risk across large groups
clearly one of the the distinctions
between I think life and health
insurances and and Property and Casualty
and insurance is um the length or the
duration
um of the the risks that are that are
being underwritten
um and protected against so in in our
case Insurance contractual obligations
for life insurance for example can last
many many decades uh 50 Years or or even
longer think of somebody that's in their
20s or 30s uh seeks of life insurance uh
and that insurance could cover till
they're 80 90 potentially even longer so
quite a long period of time
um pricing is typically fixed at the at
the outset uh my name is uh presentation
she mentioned that they would
um have annual uh adjustments
uh the other thing that's important to
note is that once it plays permanent
life insurance remains in force until
the death of the insured again that
points to the long-term nature of it
um that's subject to premiums being paid
and the other important Point here is to
note that if you get insurance it's a
permanent insurance it's in place you're
paying your premiums even if you have an
adverse information so let's say you
have a health condition that comes up
that doesn't affect your insurance you
it continues to be in place you can
continue to buy the premiums
um that that you that you have been told
you you have to pay and that doesn't
affect either the cost of your insurance
or that it's in force so that speaks to
when in when an insurance company looks
up front at assessing assessing an
individual's risk they are doing that
um not just for that point in time but
also assessing the the likelihood of
risk throughout the duration of that
contract
and so that brings us to what we we hear
the term underwriting or risk assessment
another uh term that can be used uh
similarly is classification
and and in our case how is risk
assessment determined
um
insurers will look uh at a number of
factors
um age uh certainly your your family
history your your health
uh your lifestyle things like smoking uh
occupation if it happens to carry uh
risk with it
um and they will come to a determination
on what your risk profile is now and and
what it's likely to be uh in the years
to come
the assessment is objective
um and as mentioned in a previous slide
treat equal risk equally and
differentials must be must be valid or
evidence-based
and and then as I just mentioned on the
previous slide or the previous slide
premiums relate to your mortality or
your morbidity risk in any future year
and I'm just referring back to group and
individual insurance so it's a group
insurance is provided through the
workplace could be a union or an
association
um and another distinction between group
and individual is that there are
different underwriting processes for
them uh for group uh it's price based on
characteristics of the group as a whole
as opposed to the individual him or
herself
um and there's a simplified risk
assessment for for that that group
um and it's typically designed as
temporary coverage so for example as
long as you're with that employer
now why do people need life insurance
I think one of the the clearest uh
objectives is if if I am to die for
example I want to protect my family from
a financial perspective so that
um if I'm not alive I'm not earning an
income there's a replacement stream of
funds that they can use to to for
example
um support my wife my children and so on
there are other issues from a financial
perspective one would be to pay off a
loan or mortgage that may be associated
with our financials a charitable gift is
is is an aspect that people that use
life insurance for and there's also
another example would be equalizing
bequest so for example here we know a
daughter gets the family business or
college and the life insurance could go
to a a a son for example so that they
have equal Financial benefits
um I think this in terms of why you need
life insurance it is ultimately a
personal decision about
what and how much you need
um and it can vary from from Individual
to individual but the important aspect
is that it is there to protect you and
again your loved ones
and I just touched on how much insurance
is needed that's a very common question
um and we'll go through a few aspects
here and if this may be a an item for a
discussion later but really what you're
trying to do is estimate the potential
of financial loss if if you are to die
and how you do that is
you do A needs assessment so what are
your what what incoming Capital needs
exist after your death
and then what income and capital sources
will there be
um and then life insurance is intended
to fill any shortfall between the needs
and the sources and and so this will
depend on a whole range of factors that
can be your age your number of
dependents your obligations uh as well
as personal choices of how how much
protection you want to provide for loved
ones there are a number of rules of
thumb that I've heard uh some have
suggested uh you you could need 10 times
your your salary so for example you have
you made fifty thousand dollars a year
you could look at five hundred thousand
dollars uh in life insurance so
um but there's no one set rule there uh
it's it's important to really do an
assessment and and see what makes sense
for you and financial advisors can be
very helpful in that respect
and if we looked at at types of
insurance I think the the two most
common
um categories if you will one is term
insurance
um and as a the name dictates or sort of
suggests uh this is for a certain period
of time you can you know Pick 5 10 20
years to cover a certain period of time
um one of the the common reasons this is
looked at quite closely or it was
beneficial to Consumers
um is it is a cost effective uh method
or has low cost uh and covers a period
of where there's risk for example When
Your Children Are Young
um it does provide
minimal or no savings element that's an
important element and it usually
contains a rate for the policy holder to
convert to permanent insurance or
coverage without a newer risk risk
assessment by the insurer
uh and and versus
um permanent insurance it's it's more
straightforward I would say so if we
look at permanent insurance this meets
lifelong protection needs so in addition
to death protection there also it has
cash values that are accumulated and can
be used for financial emergencies or
supplement retirement income
and premiums can be paid over a set
number of years or for for life and and
two of the the common
um
elements referred to here are whole life
versus universal life and whole life
insurance the insurer takes on both the
risk related to death and the underlying
uh investment risk whereas with
universal life
um that allows consumers to select and
change premium levels and investment
options while the insurer assumes the
risk related to death
so that one can be more complicated and
can be more costly up front
and with that I will stop sharing my
screen and turn it over to the other
speakers
Brent we have one question that has come
in and just it and it's asking if any
kind of driving history or history like
that would impact life insurance
premiums
um I'm not aware of now the only thing
that comes to mind there is anything
that is
um if you are doing racing as a
profession which carries risk there but
but not not if you are have been caught
speeding for example
perfect thank you
okay so thank you very much Brent
and now we if Brent can go off screen
and we're going to bring in our
panelists
um Ivan Jane and mathura I'm going to
ask you
to introduce yourselves briefly
it stops me from actually having to
pronounce names which I am terrible at
so
um
Ivan can we will do Ivan Jane and
mathura and you can introduce yourselves
and then I'll start asking the questions
thank you Pat and hello everyone thanks
a lot you know for connecting today my
name is Ivan Arturo I'm a certified
financial planner and I've been in the
business of financial planning for the
last 50 years and I am associated with
sunlight Financial
Jane
the eight years I'm also like Evan I'm
also a certified financial planner so
I'm quite focused on helping families
and small business owners to build a
strong financial foundation and grow
that well thank you Emma Thora hi
everyone my name is Miss Sarah there Bob
Marquette I've been the financial
advisor with sunlight for eight years
now as well uh and I'm happy to be here
great
so we're going to build on what we've
just heard from the two associations
with probably some real real life
examples as well so I will start with
you and what is insurance at a high
level and why does anybody need it
well you know what we have already had
you know a few times you know from Brand
as well insurance is just to protect you
know your major assets like you know
insurance normally is a contract that is
between the consumer and the insurance
company and is which is normally paid by
premiums and those premiums is just in
exchange you know for you to receive
financial compensation or reimbursement
against any loss can be you know like
what they mentioned before about a
casualty insurance which is car but also
in our business more for illness injury
or any premature death normally all
these premiums are paid to the insurance
companies and in our business with the
majority of the cases is just to protect
that income you know and you want to
make sure that you want to keep all the
family members they want to keep you
know the same lifestyle in case of it
were to happen to any of your family
members
so it's physical contribute to insurance
and the consumer
and and that's the same for any type of
insurance not just life insurance it can
be for any type of insurance and I think
the question was why why do we need it
as well yeah yeah so insurance is just
you know super tech you know I tell
clients is to protect your major asset
like sometimes when I ask these
questions I say you know what's your
major asset and sometimes people say oh
my house you know maybe my car but
actually that's not your major asset the
major asset that everyone has is the
ability for you to generate an income
and that's what people have insurance
just to protect your family against the
loss of that income so we normally when
we create you know Financial plans for
our clients we recommend insurance as
part of your overall Financial solid
financial plan for you know for the for
the families even for also for business
owners so we want to make sure you know
that you have you know that protection
in place because you need to predict
what's important first which I mentioned
before is your ability for you to
generate an income that's why you know
we normally recommend clients to have
you know protection in place before
moving moving on to any wealth
management or any savings component of
your financial plan
it's a great way to look at it
Jane with third do you have anything to
add to that
yeah one thing I want to add is the you
know life is quite the the unexpected
events can happen right so I I remember
I had a
client came in with his husband and his
husband has been much younger than she
is so anyway we were even like a joking
you know we said oh you know uh like the
husband said oh I have to change your
diaper one day but yeah so but the last
year I got a phone call unfortunately uh
from my clients you know her husband
passed away due to heart attack
uh so I'm fortunate that at the time
when they when both of them came in you
know meet me and then we uh locked in
life insurance for her husband as well
uh so she was able to receive a claim
check and uh use it as a down payment
for her new home now uh so yeah so just
to wonder you know say it's um we need
to protect ourselves before we move on
to any solid financial plan
it's always one of those things we don't
want to talk about because it's a very
difficult conversation to have but it's
always best to plan when things are good
just to
have security when things do go bad
right so
um it's an important conversation to
definitely always have
absolutely
so Jane the very easy question how much
does somebody need
oh yeah so I think Brett talked quite a
bit about you know uh how to calculate
the coverage amount uh so I I let if
we're talking about life insurance I
think the key is that you know you need
to think about it's you buying life
insurance not for yourself you're buying
it for your family right for the people
who depend on you so you know ask
yourself what if something will happen
to me what would my family need
so the common things we would consider
is you know how much annual income would
the family will lose right and how much
is the family expenses at the moment and
how much is your mortgage and the loan
and the debts and also estimate what
would be the tax liability come you know
into with the death so in the funerals
and other final expenses
um and also we take into consideration
how much of the existing life insurance
coverage you have right so as Brad
mentioned the common the general rule
people talk about is oh okay 10 times of
your annual salary uh that's all good uh
that can be like a basic you know
calculation you can do but also most of
the life insurance companies have an
online calculator you can utilize and it
walks you through the process and so you
can come up you know a pretty solid
number and you can you know use it as a
guideline uh but if you have the uh like
the extensive family uh you have a
business as well if the situation is a
bit more complicated I would recommend
you know work with the financial planner
uh do a needs analysis and have a more
comprehensive sort of calculation to
help you out
it's a great idea the last the last
presentation we had was about Estate
Planning and it was very clear that
insurance pays out rather quickly so
that
you think you have the money coming from
the estate but it could take you know
six months to a year before you get that
so if nothing else the life insurance
could be that cushion to get you to when
the estate is paid so that's also
something to to remember thank you
so mathura Brent did speak about the
difference between whole life and turn
but how does somebody decide what they
should use
so I always like to ask the question why
for this it's like why do you want this
insurance do you want it for when
something happens or if some if
something happens right so if they
answer they if they say something like
um I want this coverage for when I pass
away that my family is taken care of
that their funeral cost is taken care of
the empathic and Legacy onto my kids or
I want to donate funds to like a charity
or things like that and oftentimes
permanent insurance would solve that
problem because permanent Insurance
because of there is no expiration date
we know that for sure there will be a
payout right
um if the if they respond back and tell
me you know I want to make sure if I
passed away
um I want my mortgage to be taken care
of or if something happens during x
amount of years I want to make sure my
kids are taking care of my family is
taking care of my income is replaced
then oftentimes term insurance might
make the most sense
um term insurance I like to think of it
as to protect a need that's temporary
right so a mortgage for example if you
get a mortgage today 10 20 years down
the road the hope is that we'll pay down
the mortgage right so you won't meet
that huge liability so you don't need
that amount of coverage for like so you
might only need it for a duration so
term insurance might make sense or if
you have young kids again 10 20 years
down the road if they're in their 20s or
older than that they might become more
independent and less relying on yourself
so you might not need to have insurance
forever right so it really comes to
whether if it's a temporary need or a
lifelong planning need
um that kind of impacts whether you need
term insurance or permanent insurance
okay
Ivan and Jane do you have anything to
add to that
I guess you know something to mention in
that is that insurance proceeds are
tax-free benefits because sometimes
people ask you know is that insurance
proceed taxable do I have to pay taxes
on those proceeds so under the insurance
act all Insurance procedures are
tax-free so people don't have to pay any
taxes on the amount that they receive at
time of day that would be something very
important to consider
yeah
yeah great okay
um so I've been back to you what is the
difference between Group insurance and
personal insurance and does somebody
need both or one or the other
well I guess you know Group Insurance is
normally offer you know to the consumers
you know aspiring compensation package
when you're working for a company and it
normally provides you know Health dental
life insurance and also disability
protection sometimes
however when it comes to the life
insurance protection normally is not
enough coverage so we normally recommend
clients you know to have an individually
on coverage just to top it up that
benefit normally you know through the
group benefits you have about twice your
salary so if you're someone who's making
let's say you know fifty thousand
dollars a year then the life insurance
protection through the group is only a
hundred thousand but in case you have a
family members you have kids you have a
mortgage a hundred thousand is not going
to cut it right so the program relying
on group coverage is that coverage goes
until the age of 65 that's number one
because that's when you get retired and
then the group benefit is gone and no
one guarantees insurability factor which
is your health so when it comes to
insurability means you know like there
is a moment in life that you're in
trouble for you to get for you know get
coverage and there's a moment in life
that you are not in trouble anymore and
that becomes because of your health so
you have any health condition that you
why you won't be able to qualify for a
policies anymore or it's going to be
very expensive for you to pay for
premiums so that's why we normally
recommend clients you know what you you
should have on top of your group benefit
which is great that you have try to have
your individually owned policies such as
life or maybe critical illness just to
compensate actually compensate to make
sure you have you know all the overall
coverage through the group plus the
individual plans and keep in mind that
normally when you're working for a
company and the company sponsors those
plans so it's great to have them but do
not rely on them 100 because most of the
coverage are not enough it's
specifically you know for you you know
for the family needs
came in and I thought instead of waiting
till the end I'll ask it because it ties
it in is group related life insurance
only pays to the client who passes away
because of his work it's not related
with work unexpected
oh I apologize person who's asking the
question uh with work unexpectedly as
well
I think if I understood that question
correctly I think the member is asking
if someone passes away and it has to be
a work related death that that needs to
be paid the answer is no it can be for
any type of death so you have you know
the group policy to your employer and
you have a life insurance if there is
any death you know cause either at work
of work the insurance company should
compensate for that so yeah so it
doesn't matter maybe they're confused
maybe with the workers compensation
which is the disability benefit they
have at work and that's only for work
related injuries right that's a
different you know
conversation
any anything to add or we'll move on
another thing is to not rely on a group
company as well just because they can
always change their mind they can always
decide to cancel the group plan as well
so then you no longer have coverage
right so it's always supportive to have
think of it as like gravy like the work
uh coverage that you're getting through
your group
um it's always good to have your
personal coverage as well yeah that's
amazing so also yeah sorry yeah so also
I mean the work landscape is quite a
different nowadays right like my
father-in-law worked for fourth
Automotive uh his whole life but
nowadays my daughter works for three
different jobs and none of them are
permanent position right so we have to
take things into our own control and
have our own insurance yeah that's very
true
so Jane uh we've heard the word
insurability mentioned can you walk us
through what that means and I mean tie
it maybe to some of the TV commercials
we see about you know
buying Insurance anybody can buy it
anybody can get insurance regardless of
Health
right right yes so
um so uh are you insurable typically it
means you know uh will you be improved
approved for the insurance application
right uh uh are you insurable so
um
this is often it's it's very individual
based it's very much based on your age
and your health condition
um I mean different products have the
different requirements like for instance
you know certain clients you know have
certain health conditions they they can
be approved for life insurance no
problem uh but they may be declined for
critical illness insurance right and
also certain products like the term life
insurance if you're applying for term 30
you know uh if you're over age 55 some
companies you may be declined
uh so keep that in mind there's no you
know certain uh
like the one simple answer to this
question
um the other thing is uh you want to
lock in your insurability uh meaning
sometimes you know if I I know it's very
hard to decide between term life
insurance or permanent life insurance
because the cost can be so different and
you know when you're at a young age you
know you need a large amount of
insurance coverage right uh so it is it
is very helpful you know you you apply
for term life insurance in the premiums
low uh but the benefit of having term
life insurance at that time if you can't
afford permanent it's also because you
are able to lock in your insurability
meaning down the road uh if you you know
your budget change and your situation
change you want to have a permanent life
insurance you can convert partial of
your term life insurance into a
permanent one okay with that yeah
without any medical uh underwriting so
that's called the Locking insurability
which is very important
um well back to the question you
answered about those commercials
it's very hard to say I think the
question you need to ask yourself is you
know if you were diagnosed with the
life-threatening you know critical
illness
uh do you think you will be able insured
for life insurance right insurance
companies all about assessing risks so
how much risk those insurance companies
are willing to take and at what costs
so uh so I would say it's you know uh
always reach out and to to to to try not
get an assessment uh but when you're
healthy you know uh plan ahead yeah
that's that's a very good point very
good point
anything to add before we move on
or Ivan no
no I think you know we mentioned already
about the underwriting process and
normally when we submit an insurance
application we go through a process
called underrated which we already
mentioned and that's what we assess all
the risk so what Jay mentioned is you
know basically you are you unhealthy as
long as you are in good you know Health
go ahead don't think it twice try to go
and apply for insurance and I go I
always tell the client you know there is
no best insurance products in the market
you have to make sure you know the the
best insurance for you is the one that
you can afford and that you can qualify
for that's the best insurance for
yourself right then down the road you
know the finances might change they
might be able to upgrade your policy you
might be able to convert it with like
what just you know Jane saying mentioned
mentioned that you can go you know we
can compare the policy to a permanent
policy with you know with non-medical
evidence so all these things can happen
but as long as you are you're unhealthy
try to buy as much as possible because
you know you will thank yourself that
you did it in the past that I would say
that is very important you know the
probability factor in this in this
manner yeah that's that's a great line
yep
okay mathura
um if I own my own home and I have
mortgage insurance
that I got when I you know from the bank
or the financial institution that I got
my mortgage from do I need any other
kind of insurance
um
with the bank so there's you
the banks always have to ask you to get
mortgage insurance right because they're
giving you a huge loans they want to
make sure that if something happens to
you that they're getting their money
back right so there is a difference
between mortgage insurance that the bank
versus getting like a term insurance to
cover your mortgage the mortgage
insurance at the bank is considered like
a decrease in coverage and what I mean
by that so say you have a half a million
dollar in your mortgage and they say
your premium your Market insurance
premium for that is a hundred dollars
every month you're paying down your
mortgage so your balance is decreasing
right
um but you're still paying a hundred
dollars that same hundred dollars and if
something would happen
um say when the balance is now two
hundred thousand all the bank is going
to do is pay off that balance
right so whereas if you were to get a
term insurance to cover that mortgage
it's a level coverage meaning if
something were to happen down the road
your beneficiary would then just they
would get the full half a million they
would then decide whether they want to
pay off the mortgage balance and they
can even keep the remaining for their
like like uh lifestyle and ongoing
expenses so it's more beneficial
mortgage insurance we shouldn't only
think about life insurance or term
insurance or mortgage insurance to
protect your mortgage so that's
considered a
um so another thing to consider it's
critical illness insurance or disability
insurance
um because critical illness Insurance
disability insurance is a living benefit
so while you're alive if you're ever
sick or disabled or injure yourself
um and you're off of work you need to
have like an income replacement right so
critical illness Insurance can help you
with that you're able to get a lump sum
payment
um to cover so if you're off of work for
a few years or or even if it's a short
period of time at least gives you that
ability to not worry about your
financials and to focus on recovery
is there a difference in cost between
mortgage insurance and term insurance
or does is it it depends again it's a
depend situation but oftentimes from
what I've seen term insurance is a lot
cheaper another difference between
mortgage insurance at the bank versus
term insurance is that at the bank the
mortgage the bank is actually the
beneficiary right so whereas if it's a
term insurance your family is the
beneficiary and they'll they also do
something called
um post underwriting so at the time of
application they just ask you maybe like
five or six yes or no questions
um and at the time of think that's when
they start doing the underwriting and it
causes a lot of issues and problems a
lot of times whereas with an insurance
company we do all our underwriting
upfront so it's all black and white it's
a contract so there's more peace of mind
and if you were to sell your property
or if your mortgage comes up for real
you don't have to constantly keep
reapplying for mortgage insurance just
because this is on your life I'll post
it being on the actual mortgage
so a question has come in so I think
it's appropriate to ask now is is it
mandatory to have house insurance or to
get house insurance when you're applying
for a mortgage
it's not mandatory but it is always
advised so the bank isn't going to
insist on it
they shouldn't
it
okay so they do have to ask they do have
to ask they shouldn't yeah it shouldn't
yeah but I know they might like pressure
you
so I guess you know in that question is
you know we normally ask clients to get
insurance from a licensed Insurance a
broker with license insurance advisor
and sometimes you know people that are
offering you know the mortgage they are
not life insurance license they work for
the mortgage maybe they have a mortgage
license but they don't have a life
license it's just maybe a part of the
process that they're doing at the bank
they need to offer that product you know
as a mortgage protection but the
consumer has always the right to waive
it like you have there is a document
called a mortgage insurance waiver that
you can sign say you know what I'm
opting out of the insurance because
maybe I have something else through a
life insurance company so it's always
recommended you know to check the
difference between the two like what a
Mitra just explained and then you make
your you know your own your own decision
if I rent
because I mean yeah well I think you
know insurance as I mentioned before is
not about I mean what you know would you
have an apartment or you have a market
yes you need insurance we know that but
when it comes let's say you are renting
you have a spouse or you have children
and even though you know you don't own a
home you need to have insurance it's
like it's a it's a it's a part of a a
the overall Financial you know a
foundation for our clients so if you I
think you know I truly Insurance you
know as an act of Love basically that's
how you know I say insurance is an act
of love if you really love your spouse
you really love your children you need
to have coverage because it's something
were to happen to you in terms of any
death pretty much or death any sickness
or any illness you want to make sure
that you're able to put food on the
table you want to make sure that you can
send you know your kids to school
because maybe that's one of your goals
and you want to make sure that your
income is replaced because what if
there's there are no protection in place
what's going to happen to your family
you know you know finances what's going
to happen to you know how about the
dream of you saving up enough money to
buy a home that you don't have that
protection in place then all these goals
are going to go into the drain so that's
why you know it's not about having you
know like you have a house or you're
renting around if you have a spouse and
you are you know you have children or
dependents you need to have insurance
insurance I would say is an act of love
it's not for the people you know for
yourself it's for the people you leave
behind
so can a landlord insist on you having
some kind of insurance
yeah maybe yeah so maybe the question is
you know is there are like two policies
when it comes to that so there is you
know I think the content insurance or
the tenant Insurance that's a different
topic which we're not licensed to
discuss but I mean that's the content
Insurance you know that's just to
protect the things that are inside the
house and landlord normally asks for
those insurance but that's not our
expertise uh what we're expertise more
about the life you know the life
insurance great so those are our
standard the standard questions I've
written down and so we're we can invite
uh Anne-Marie and Brent to come back and
we've got a few questions that have come
in so whoever wants to answer and then
we can go Roundtable
um so the first one that's coming is if
somebody hasn't any insurance at a
retirement plan what kind of income does
a Canadian get from the government
so I guess it's more replacement income
so does the CPP and OAS is that
sufficient to retire or should there be
an insurance plan
uh going forward
who wants to take that
I'm happy to to say a couple words just
to start the discussion
um and I think in part like many of the
other answers here it starts with it
depends and what I mean by that is what
you get out of CBP or qpp uh isn't is
based on a couple of factors one how
long have you paid into it uh and two
what income level are you earning
um and so there are different
approaches as to how much income you
need
um as replacement income in retirement
uh we certainly have some financial
advisors planners here so I don't want
to speak up for them
um but I I think it's fair to say that
um as your income changes from low to
high the amount of income you may need
to replace uh also changes because
government programs will provide a base
amount but as you get to higher levels
you will need to supplement that if you
want to maintain your standard of living
in a retirement so those those would be
my initial comments and I will I will
leave it open for others to comment
yeah so I'll jump in a I would say yeah
so all the government benefits such as
you know old age security and the CPP
those are just made just to replace at
least 30 to 40 percent of your income
basically and then you know that's why
you know we encourage Canadians to start
saving us you know as soon as possible
so you can have that Compound Effect in
your Investments so when you reach the
age of 65 you don't rely 100 on the
government benefits you're able to have
the government benefits maybe just to
cover just the very very basic needs and
then you want to have enough funds maybe
for lifestyle maybe they want to you
know you want to travel maybe you wanna
you know you want to be able to cover
expenses related to your health then
that's what you need to make sure that
you have Investments and here in Canada
we have you know tfsas we have rsps so
and also you have company sponsor
pension plans so you will be able to use
all these plans to make sure that you
are you know using that on top of the
CPP or the qpp or the all the security
so we encourage African annual to as
early as possible so that way you don't
rely on the government benefits only
it's great that we have them we're very
lucky to live in Canada because we have
those benefits but the majority of the
cases that's not enough
I'll give it a second after each
question to see if anyone has anything
to add so another question that's come
in as
um if somebody owns a small business
what is the best way to make insurance I
have insurance for that if they are the
sort of the single or the sole owner if
it's a family business
yeah so um if I can take a stab on that
um so for business owners uh you you are
able to get a life insurance under the
name of the cooperation uh so the idea
is you know uh if if the corporation has
the any debt you are if the corporation
has other shareholders and you want to
do like a shareholder agreement funding
uh that you know the payout can fund
those uh those needs
um sometimes you know there there's only
if a small business only has one
shareholder it's also possible uh to
have the shareholder insured and also
the spouse as well uh but the tax
treatment is slightly different but
that's something you know probably you
know you want to talk to a content to
just to get more details on that so
again it would be more insurance on the
individual that or the people that own
the business as opposed to insurance on
the business itself right right yeah so
yeah we're talking about life insurance
yeah yeah yeah okay
so another question that's come in is I
am a full-time student but they want to
obtain insurance for hit themselves and
their family such as health insurance
how what would that look like is there
and I know most of you may not be able
to answer but is there something I guess
that's critical life that they're
referring to
um it could be criticalness or I'm not
sure if they're referring to like
personal health insurance so like health
and dental coverage
um but yeah it's just yeah we would just
sit down with them and do an application
help them with the application perfect
okay
um
so Ivan you did mention and we've all I
just mentioned too the critical
insurance and I know you don't tell but
maybe somebody can walk us through what
critical illness insurance is just so
people can get their head around if
that's something that they should have
like the kind of person if you're
working for business or do you own a
business that what kind of person should
have critical illness insurance
okay so I can jump in okay maybe you
know either Jane you know also let me
know so do you think illness insurance
is an insurance coverage that you pay
premium to the insurance company in case
of any diagnosis such as cancer heart
attack a stroke you know any heart
condition the insurance company would
pay a lumps on payment that lump sum
payment comes to you know to the
individual and there would be money
going to them tax-free now as we know
when you're working for a company and
you might have a group benefits so you
may have maybe some disability insurance
which is only an income replacement so
when I say income replacement means you
know they're just covering between 60 to
maybe 70 of your income through the
group disability coverage but there is
that 30 Gap you know between the 70 to
go into into 100. so that's what the
critical illness you know comes very
hand is to cover that Gap that's number
one number two I'm sure many of the
audience you know maybe they have a
friend they have a family member they
have it going maybe through cancer
situation which is very common and most
of the you know of the insurance
companies through work or maybe you know
through the province of Ontario there
are some expenses that are not covered
through all hip or through the
provincial insurance or even to the
insurance company and you need to make
sure you have enough financial resources
to cope with that illness so the
critical illness gives you that lump sum
payment just to covered that expense
that's number one we'll be able to close
the gap on your disability insurance
that's number two and then it gives you
that financial peace of mind so you
don't Focus about how am I going to pay
these you know now my mortgage now I
have to send my kids to school what's
going to happen to my retirement I have
to pull out money for an rsps all these
things have a lot of financial you know
impact on your family so you have that
critical illness Insurance it pays a
lump sum payment let's say a hundred
thousand or whatever you buy and then
you're able to get that money and then
you can cover all these you know
Financial expenses and all you need to
do is to focus on your recovery which is
what's important when you're sick you
know illness like that so that's what
the critical illness Insurance it just
gives you that peace of mind it is a
living benefit you know like you get it
when you're alive right you can use the
ammonia as you wish it is not a
reimbursement program because some
people you know think okay I have to get
expenses and then get paid no if you buy
a hundred thousand dollars a lot of
critical illness Insurance a time of
claim if you're approved for the claim
they give you the check and then you can
use it as you wish and then you can you
know cover any expenses the majority of
the case is for you just to focus on on
the recovery so that's the reason why we
have you know critical elements
Insurance extremely important you know I
you know we recommend it to our clients
because we can rely only on
disabilitical protection because this
ability is only to replace your income
critical illness will be like a aspect
like a Top-Up you know on top of the
disability of protection
anybody want anything to add to that
yeah I just wouldn't say yeah like life
insurance and critical illness insurance
they go hand in hand they're both
equally just as important
um and just because you have group
benefits that doesn't mean you
automatically have disability insurance
it's not mandatory for companies to
sponsor them in their package
um so just keep which makes it even more
of a need to also look into critical
illness Insurance
um just because like
with the way our lifestyle is going I
mean knock on where we hope everyone
lives well and it has a healthy life but
anything can happen at any time and you
just won't always want to have that
protection and oftentimes people can
even people come to us when something
happens which at that point it's too
late right
um so you want to have that discussion
when you're young and healthy
very good answer
there are no more questions in the queue
I'm looking at all the speakers is there
anything after listening to all the
presentations in the in the conversation
that you want to just stress or to add
that either hasn't been said or you
think is important to end the
presentation with maybe I'll go around
so Ivan will start with you and then
just go around with everybody sure thank
you
okay so I think the best advice you know
for everyone is to start you know
looking for a financial advisor or a
certified financial planner and the
reason why because you know financial
planners they look at your overall
financial situation we're able to see
you know like you have group benefits
what is it that you have what are your
financial goals that you want to achieve
in a short term you know like in a short
term or long term we also look at you
know what's the wealth management when
it comes to Investments and also what
we're talking today which is the risk
management Factor so if you're working
with a financial advisor don't only
focus only on one single wealth
Investments or Insurance try to look at
the holistic Financial picture of your
finances so when you're working with the
planner we look at you know everything
and then try to make sure that you have
a written financial plan so written
financial plan is different that you
walk into the bank and then you're going
to buy a product is different a written
financial plan you have like a roadmap
for you to follow to make sure that you
go step by step according to your
financial goals some recommendations you
know start looking for a financial
planner there are you know tons of
resources online I think there is a
website from FP Canada that you can
search you know for names and people who
are certified financial planners and you
will be able to see you know the people
that may be some bios and maybe that's
matching and even you know through Sun
Life also we have the sunlive.ca we have
something called advisor match so
actually you wanna you know search
online for advisor match at sunlife.ca
website you will be able to look at you
know who I want to work with maybe you
know you want to make sure they speak
your language and you want to make sure
no maybe it's ready to you that you will
be able to match it you know with the
person you know you want to work with
but get an advisor and get a written
financial plan that would be my advice
to the audience
for thorough
um yeah just just to echo on what Ivan
said um you know financial planning is
something important that you need to do
it is like I said Eric mentioned earlier
it can be a very difficult topic for a
lot of people
um but it is important to have that
conversation
um on top of even financial planning
even having like things like a will in
place right so oftentimes people forget
about how important that is too
um so
um yeah so just start that conversation
don't put it off to I'll do it later
I'll do it later because like I said
anything can happen we've seen so many
situations and
um it's just better to be prepared it's
just a piece of mind to to plan ahead
great thank you Jane anything to add
yeah so I just want to add you know
financial planning is not to just for
people you know have lots of assets and
even though you know you may have a very
simple you know investment account so
that you have a very simple family
situation
um it is still advisable to to get a
financial plan uh one thing because we
we talked about retirement planning all
right so one thing we can do is you know
we can actually work backwards you know
you tell us your retirement goal what
kind of lifestyle you want right how
much you need every month to spend
during your retirement period we work
backwards and help you to calculate how
much you needed to save nowadays right
so you at least you have a goal in your
mind you know to going forward
so don't hesitate to reach out to a
financial planner if even though you
have a very simple situation
very good advice Brent do you have
anything in conclusion
so I I wrote down two things when you
asked the question in terms of what I
would stress I think there's a common
theme here uh one one is have a plan but
but my focus would have been and I think
it's been said is the earlier or the
younger you can get insurance in place
the better
um it just makes a lot of sense in terms
of people are generally healthier uh and
and have better access to Insurance when
they're young so so I would stress that
the other thing that that I would stress
um is that insurance is a competitive
market
um insurers will focused on different
elements of insurance and they have
different risk tolerances and so really
what that what I'm trying to say there
is that if you have challenges getting
insurance or getting insurance at a
premium that that you are comfortable
with you can always shop around with
other insurers whether that's you doing
it directly or through an advisor so so
those would be sort of the two points
that I would leave with
great and Anne-Marie we'll end with you
thank you I just want to mention uh
twice um home insurance has come up in
the conversation with the panelists and
that's kind of my baileywick so I wanted
to stress that if you're getting a
mortgage most lenders will require that
you have home insurance on the property
before they forward you any funds for
the mortgage so that's something to keep
in mind and another thing for those of
you who rent
given that the rental market in in
Toronto and in Ontario actually is
getting so competitive many landlords
are starting to require that the people
that they rent to have tenant insurance
just for you tenant insurance is not
very expensive I did a little quote
before we came on here
um for for forty thousand dollars worth
of your property coverage uh it would
cost around three hundred dollars a year
so you know what is that like twenty
dollars or so a month so just keep those
things in mind I know it's a lot of
insurance but in my mind better to have
too much than not enough in all of the
lines that we talked about today
and just one question that has come in
quickly before we wrap up is is there a
provincial
um I guess is it provincially regulated
so somebody is saying they live in
Manitoba so can they get life insurance
from an advisor in Ontario
um so are there provincial restrictions
okay so I'll answer down so yes there
are a you know it is up we're all
provincial license so you will need to
look you know for an advisory Province
who is licensed in your Province now
there are advisors in Ontario that have
different licensing different provinces
so you can also check with that but the
best option you know to go you know to
maybe the website to check you know for
insurance license advisors in your
Province because it's Insurance you know
is provision provision regulated
right but I think I think Paula has a
question is that did you have no
no okay
no I just saw her hand that's right
so thank you so much everybody I think
this has been incredibly helpful for
anybody who is looking to buy a house or
life insurance and stressing out the
importance of life insurance because I
think people
um I think we heard it a lot today
people are not comfortable with that
discussion and don't want to think about
when somebody passes away but you've
made it really clear that you have to
and I love Ivan I love your line that
it's it's showing your love for those
people that you're leaving behind if
something does happen to you so think
about that as well and I would think too
even thinking about those people that
maybe not working outside the home how
much would it cost you to have the
services that that person does whether
it's daycare or child care
so you may want a small policy on them
as well
so thank you all for participating I
I've saw lots of of great material
coming through the chat so hopefully
everybody gets a hold of that
information as well and with that we
will close and we will be back in two
weeks to talk about ETFs something I
actually will know something about
thanks very much everybody thank you
very much thank you for invite
thank you